Finding Aid for Tivadar Balogh papers, 1946-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Tivadar Balogh papers 1946-1998, 1960-1997
Balogh, Tivadar
47 oversize folders
6.25 linear feet
2009189 Aa 2
Plymouth, Michigan based architect, active 1946-1997, and former University of Michigan College of Architecture and Design instructor (1956-1997), known for his design work, and association with architect and former University of Michigan Dean of the College of Architecture and Urban Planning Robert C. Metcalf. Balogh's work included approximately 150 residential, institutional, and commercial projects in Michigan, Illinois, and Arizona. The papers in this collection include correspondence, slides and photographs, clippings, teaching materials, project files, and architectural drawings.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Accession received through Dorothy Balogh in 2008 (donor no. 10126 ).
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The Balogh papers are open with the exception of some student related files.
The Balogh papers includes restricted material in the following categories:
Student Academic Records -- Box 7
Tivadar Balogh, architect, was born December 16, 1926, in Detroit, Michigan, the son of Hungarian immigrants. Following his high school graduation in 1944, Balogh enlisted in the U.S. Navy and served in World War II (1945-1946), before enrolling at the University of Michigan on a track scholarship in 1946. While at Michigan, Balogh received the Harley, Ellington & Day architectural scholarship (1951) and an academic honor from the professional fraternity Tau Sigma Delta (1952). Balogh graduated with a degree from the College of Architecture in 1952, and served another tour in the Navy during the Korean War (1952-1954), prior to engaging in professional practice.
Balogh worked as an instructor at Michigan's College of Architecture and Design throughout most of his career. He taught at the university as a visiting lecturer (1956, 1963), instructor in the extension service (1964-1970), adjunct instructor (1972-1985), and adjunct professor (1985-1997). Balogh also taught graphic design development for two years at Schoolcraft College in Livonia, Michigan (1970-1971). During his tenure in the College of Architecture, Balogh taught classes in communication skills, visual studies, construction materials and methods, building and comprehensive design, and graphics, earning high regard from colleagues and students alike. In 1973, Balogh received the Sol King Award for Excellence in Teaching from the college.
Balogh began his professional architecture career as a draftsman for Detroit mechanical engineer Andrew F. Caughey (1946) and Detroit architect Earl Confer (1947-1948). From 1949 through 1952, Balogh was employed as a designer and draftsman for the Detroit firm of O'Dell, Hewlett & Luckenbach. Beginning in 1954, Balogh began work for fellow Michigan alumnus, and future dean of the College of Architecture, Robert Metcalf (1950), working as one of Metcalf's draftsmen through 1960. Between 1960 and 1961 Balogh worked as an architect and designer for the firms of Shreve, Walker, and Associates and W.B. Ford Design Associates, both of Detroit.
In 1961, Balogh began his own private practice, based in Plymouth, Michigan, doing modernist residential and commercial work. Balogh's practice was small, at times consisting of Balogh alone or Balogh assisted by two or three other draftsmen or architects. While Balogh often produced the mechanical and structural drawings on his own, he also worked with a number of consultants, including Robert M. Darvas and Associates, DiClementi & Siegal Engineering, Norman L. Dietrich Associates, and Construction Services Company. By the time of his retirement Balogh had completed approximately 150 residential, institutional, and commercial projects throughout Michigan, Illinois, and Arizona.
In addition to his teaching and professional work, Balogh committed himself to public and professional service. Balogh served on the Plymouth Township Planning Commission (1960-1966), and in 1980 designed the logo for the township's official seal. Balogh engaged in architectural service and research, as well, as a participant in the University of Michigan's Architecture Research Lab, a member of the Schoolcraft Community College Architectural Advisory Committee, architectural advisor for the Township of Canton Historical Commission, member of the Plymouth-Canton School District Architectural Program Advisory Committee, board member of the Michigan Society of Architects, and as treasurer (1965), vice-president (1966), and president (1967) of the Huron Valley chapter of the American Institute of Architects (AIA).
A talented artist and respected architect, Balogh was the recipient of numerous awards for his work including an Honorable Mention, with Robert C. Metcalf, for a youth center in the Porcelain Enamel Design Competition (1956); Honorable Mention, with Robert C. Metcalf and William A. Werner, for a house in the Morton Arboretum House Competition (1956); a Merit Award, in collaboration with the office of Robert C. Metcalf, from the 18th Annual National Conference on Church Architecture for the Church of the Good Shepherd (1958); two design awards from Progressive Architecture for the Balogh Residence (1957) and the Tennis and Swim Club of Plymouth, Michigan (1972); the Governor's Award for Excellence of Design in Michigan for the Mercy College of Detroit library addition (1977); a Citation of Merit from the American Plywood Association for the remodeling of Growth Works (1981); the Huron Valley AIA Lifetime Service Award (1998); and the AIA Michigan President's Award (1998), for outstanding contributions to the community and the profession.
Tivadar Balogh retired from the University of Michigan and private architectural practice in 1997. Balogh died on December 1, 2006.
The papers of Tivadar Balogh include correspondence, slides and photographs, clippings, teaching materials, project files, and architectural drawings. The papers are organized into five series: Audio-Visual, Biographical Materials, Office Files, Teaching, and Drawings.
Subjects:
Architects--United States.; Architecture--Arizona.; Architecture--Designs and plans.; Architecture--Illinois.; Architecture--Michigan.; Architecture, Domestic--Designs and plans.; Balogh, Tivadar.; Metcalf, Robert Clarence, 1923-; University of Michigan. College of Architecture and Design.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Genre/Form:
Architectural drawings.; Architectural records.
- Audio-Visual Materials undated, 1998
  The Audio-Visual series, undated and 1998 (1.25 linear feet), consists of audio and visual materials documenting Balogh's teaching career and architectural projects. Included in the series are photographs and slides of Balogh's students' work, Balogh and his colleagues, and Balogh's residential, industrial, and commercial buildings. Also in the series are video (VHS) and audio tapes of Balogh's 1998 American Institute of Architects awards, and unlabeled microfilm reels of Balogh's building projects.
  - Audio-Video Materials
    - American Institute of Architects Huron Valley Holiday Party 1998, VHS (Box 1)
    - Architectural Projects, microfilm (Box 1)
      (9 small unlabelled rolls of 35mm film on spindles in one microfilm box)
    - Tiv Balogh American Institute of Architects Award 1998, Audio cassette (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - Architectural Project Photographs, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Balogh House Photographs (Box 1)
    - People (Box 1)
  - Slides
    - Architectural Slides (Box 2)
      - Anderson Residence 1964 (Box 2)
      - "Architecture without Architects", 4 boxes (Box 2)
      - Asco Model Shots (Box 2)
      - Ash Residence 1968 (Box 2)
      - Balogh Residence, Scheme II Model (Abandoned) 1958 (Box 2)
      - Clark House, Ann Arbor, MI 1963 (Box 2)
      - Constant House (Box 2)
      - de Bear Residence (Box 2)
      - Fabian Residence (Box 2)
      - Frank Lloyd Wright (Box 2)
      - Gasdick-Ritzehein Residence, Ypsilanti, MI 1970 (Box 2)
      - Goddard Building, Plymouth, MI 1968 (Box 2)
      - Growthworks of Ann Arbor, MI (Box 2)
      - Heide's Flowers, Plymouth, MI 1967 (Box 2)
      - Industrialized Housing, 6 boxes (Box 2)
      - Johnston-McGregor Residence (Box 2)
      - Lauff Residence (Box 2)
      - Lundy Residence, Barton Hills, MI 1970 (Box 2)
      - Mac Lellan House (Box 2)
      - McCarthy Residence (Box 2)
      - Niblett Carport (Box 2)
      - Northville State Dorms (Box 2)
      - Office 1967 (Box 2)
      - Other's Work and Miscellaneous (Box 2)
      - Plymouth Department of Public Works Building 1962 (Box 2)
      - Prizlow House 1966 (Box 2)
      - Professional Pavilion for Robert Meek 1968 (Box 2)
      - Marshall Field House, Chicago, IL 1966 (Box 2)
      - Mercy College of Detroit, 1 carousel and four boxes (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous and Office (Box 2)
      - Models and Renderings, 2 carousels (Box 2)
      - Saper Residence (Box 2)
      - St. Clair Metro Beach work with Oldell, Hewlett & Luckenbach (Box 2)
      - "Street Scaping Sketches" (Box 2)
      - Tennis Club` (Box 2)
      - WB Ford Pavilion 1961 (Box 2)
      - Work with Metcalf 1954-1959 (Box 2)
      - Work with W.B. Ford 1961 (Box 2)
      - Yost Elementary School, Detroit, MI (Box 2)
      - Zelek Residence, 3 boxes (Box 2)
    - Teaching Slides
      - Lecture Shots and Student Boards, UM Architecture 552 1983 (Box 2)
      - Architecture 551/552 1992-1993 (Box 2)
- Biographical Materials 1946-1997
  The records in the Biographical Materials series, 1946-1997, (0.25 linear feet) outline details of Balogh's personal life and professional career. Materials in this series include Balogh's college transcripts, his curricula vitae and resumes, remembrances and obituaries, and Naval service records.
  - Curricula vitae and Resumes (Box 3)
  - Naval Service Records (Box 3)
  - Remembrances (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan Transcripts (Box 3)
- Office Files 1956-1998
  The Office Files series, 1956-1998, (3 linear feet) document Balogh's architectural work for his own private practice, as well as his work with Robert Metcalf. The series is divided into two subseries: Administrative Materials and Project Files. The administrative materials subseries includes records documenting Balogh's professional accreditation, awards, project portfolios, clippings, advisory committee work, as well as financial information relating to Balogh's practice. The project files subseries is organized by project name and includes client correspondence, billing information, design development materials, sketches, and renderings. While some files include materials that document the entire architectural lifecycle of a project, other files have only partial project documentation.
  - Administrative Materials
    - Architectural Advisory Committees
      - Plymouth-Canton Community Schools (Box 3)
      - Schoolcraft College (Box 3)
    - Awards
      - Huron Valley American Institute of Architects Awards and Recognitions (Box 3)
      - Plywood Design Award (Box 3)
      - Porcelain Enamel Design Competition (Box 3)
      - Progressive Architecture, 1957 (Box 3)
      - Progressive Architecture, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Sol King Award for Excellent Teaching in Architecture (Box 3)
    - Correspondence (Box 3)
    - General Specifications (Box 3)
    - Incorporation Records, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Joint Ventures, Balogh-Fisher (Box 3)
    - Letters of Recommendation (Box 3)
    - Klement, Michael (Box 3)
    - Logo Design (Box 3)
    - Office Brochure, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Plymouth Symphony (Box 3)
    - Portfolios
      - Constant Residence (Box 3)
      - Growth Works of Ann Arbor (Box 3)
      - Office Space (Box 3)
      - Mercy College of Detroit
        - Library Addition, 2 folders (Box 3)
        - Sciences Building, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Residences (Box 4)
      - Sports Complexes (Box 4)
    - Professional Registrations
      - American Institute of Architects (Box 4)
      - Michigan State Board of Registration (Box 4)
      - National Council of Architectural Registration Boards, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Project Proposals (Box 4)
    - Project Sketches (Box 4)
    - Robert Darvis Associates, P.C. (Box 4)
  - Project Files
    - Aardema, Hedy, Ontario, June 30, 1993, 2 folders
      - Correspondence (Box 4)
      - Design Development and Architectural Drawings and Materials (Box 4)
    - Balogh, Tivadar and Dorothy, Plymouth, MI, 5 folders
      - Garage 1985 (Box 4)
      - General (Box 4)
      - Media and Awards (Box 4)
      - Photographs (Box 4)
      - Sketches, Renderings, and Models (Box 4)
    - Beck, Charles and Janice Beck, Ann Arbor, MI June 13, 1991, 2 folders
      - Correspondence (Box 4)
      - Design Development and Architectural Drawings and Materials (Box 4)
    - Burye, Mark and Gerri, Ann Arbor, MI August 6, 1987 (Box 4)
    - Callow, Mr. and Mrs. James, Livonia, MI January 26, 1990 (Box 4)
    - Canton Christian Church of God, Canton, MI December 15, 1994 (Box 4)
    - Chen, Michael and Ruth, Ann Arbor, MI January 23, 1993, 2 folders
      - Correspondence (Box 4)
      - Design Development Drawings and Materials (Box 4)
    - Clark, Samuel K., Ann Arbor, MI July 22, 1981 (Box 4)
    - Cole, Dean and Carolyn, Ann Arbor, MI May 10, 1991 (Box 4)
    - Colony Swim Club, Canton, MI March 7, 1994, 2 folders
      - Correspondence (Box 4)
      - Design Development and Architectural Drawings and Materials (Box 4)
    - Day, Colin and Jennifer, Ann Arbor, MI May 1, 1992 (Box 4)
    - de Bear, Mr. and Mrs. Richard, Plymouth, MI, Residence, June 23,1978, 2 folders
      - Correspondence (Box 4)
      - Design Development and Architectural Drawings and Materials (Box 4)
    - Deak, Steve September 2, 1987 (Box 4)
    - Dexter Library Alteration, Dexter, MI August 19, 1992 (Box 4)
    - Fairmont Builders, 4 folders (Box 5)
      - Abbott Parkside, Okemos, MI March 21, 1990, 2 folders
        - Correspondence (Box 5)
        - Design and Architectural Drawings and Materials (Box 5)
      - Emerald Lake, East Lansing November 1987, 2 folders
        - Correspondence (Box 5)
        - Design Development and Architectural Drawings and Materials (Box 5)
      - Multiple Housing, East Lansing May 14, 1987 (Box 5)
    - Forbes, Mr. and Mrs. Larry, Plymouth, MI June 10, 1997
      - Correspondence (Box 5)
      - Design Development and Architectural Drawings and Materials (Box 5)
    - Ford III, Mr. and Mrs. Walter B., Grosse Pointe, MI May 12, 1988 (Box 5)
    - Forrest, Dr. and Mrs. Jeffrey, Bloomfield Hills, MI February 1, 1994 (Box 5)
    - Friends of Miller Woods, Plymouth Township July 9, 1992 (Box 5)
    - Galler, Mr. and Mrs. Bernard A., Ann Arbor, MI October 10, 1991 (Box 5)
    - Growthworks, Ann Arbor, MI February 5, 1982 (Box 5)
    - Hanyi, Mr. and Mrs. Karl, Plymouth, MI January 21, 1983, 2 folders
      - Correspondence (Box 5)
      - Design Development and Architectural Drawings and Materials (Box 5)
    - Holt, George and Linda, Howell, MI October 12, 1987 (Box 5)
    - Jender, Joseph and Susan, Canton, MI August 1, 1987 (Box 5)
    - Johnson, Philip, Montague, MI July 9, 1987 (Box 5)
    - Kelleher, Tom and Linda, Ann Arbor, MI March 26, 1992 (Box 5)
    - Kirshnew, Bob and Emily, Livonia, MI December 14, 1991 (Box 5)
    - Litchfield Apartments, Litchfield, Mi December 12, 1989 (Box 5)
    - M.A. Electric, Dearborn Heights, MI July 2, 1995 (Box 5)
    - Marcoux, Jackson, MI December 22, 1994 (Box 5)
    - Mercy College of Detroit, Detroit, MI, 3 folders
      - Athletics Facility October 19, 1978 (Box 5)
      - Library Addition November 1976 (Box 5)
      - Science Building undated (Box 5)
    - Miller, Greg, Okemos, MI May 25, 1986 (Box 5)
    - Naski, Gerald and Nancy, Birmingham, MI June 6, 1991 (Box 5)
    - Northwestern Guidance Clinic, Garden City, MI May 28, 1985 (Box 5)
    - Plymouth Community Arts Council March 18, 1980 (Box 5)
    - Plymouth District Library, Plymouth, MI January 25, 1991 (Box 5)
    - Reek, Don and Alexa Gordon, Whitmore Lake, MI August 11, 1993 (Box 5)
    - Rojek, Matthew and Betty, Plymouth, MI September 9, 1992 (Box 5)
    - Roosevelt, Franklin Delano Memorial, Washington DC 1960 (Box 5)
    - Saper Galleries, East Lansing April 23, 1985, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Saper, Martin and Thelma, East Lansing, MI May 7, 1992 (Box 5)
    - Seger, Craig and Margaret, Alpenia, MI May 31, 1993 (Box 5)
    - Sloat, Mr. and Mrs. Barry, Ann Arbor, MI October 20, 1994 (Box 5)
    - Spuntech Housing Corporation, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Terhune, Tom and Donna, MI, Pinkney, MI March 3, 1996 (Box 6)
    - Thiesen, Carl, Ann Arbor, MI November 6, 1973 (Box 6)
    - Varani, James and Barbara, Ann Arbor, MI August 21, 1990 (Box 6)
    - Vaughan, Mr. and Mrs. Patrick, Ann Arbor, MI September 24, 1990 (Box 6)
    - Waidley, Tim and Melissa, Grasse Lake, MI November 28, 1993 (Box 6)
    - Wayne State University, Hungarian Heritage Room, Detroit, MI November 21, 1990 (Box 6)
- Teaching Materials (University of Michigan) 1974-1994
  The Teaching series, 1974-1994, (1.25 linear feet) contains records of Balogh's teaching at the University of Michigan. The series is divided into two subseries: Administrative Materials and Courses. The administrative materials subseries includes Balogh's academic appointments, course evaluations, and student letters of recommendation. The courses subseries has syllabi, assignments, projects, and exams for the courses Balogh taught, or co-taught, while an instructor at Michigan. Two folders are restricted since they contain student educational information (grade appeals and student letters of recommendation).
  - Administrative Materials
    - Academic Appointments (Box 6)
    - Admissions Committee (Box 6)
    - American Institute of Architects (Box 6)
    - Clippings (Box 6)
    - Course Evaluations (Box 6)
    - Grade Appeal (Box 7)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2062 ]
    - Lawrence Technological University Design Jury (Box 6)
    - Student Letters of Recommendation (Box 7)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2065 ]
    - Syllabi (Box 6)
  - Courses
    - Architecture 310-Graphics, 2 folders
      - General (Box 6)
      - 1987 (Box 6)
    - Architecture 317-Construction I, 3 folders
      - 1981 (Box 6)
      - 1983 (Box 6)
      - 1984 (Box 6)
    - Architecture 327-Materials and Methods of Construction, 3 folders
      - 1977 (Box 6)
      - 1981 (Box 6)
      - 1982 (Box 6)
    - Architecture 432-Architectural Design, 2 folders
      - 1991 (Box 6)
      - 1992 (Box 6)
    - Architecture 437-Construction 1980 (Box 6)
    - Architecture 442-Architectural Design IV, 4 folders
      - Brass Knocker Awards (Box 6)
      - 1988 (Box 6)
      - 1989 (Box 6)
      - 1990 (Box 6)
    - Architecture 509-Advanced Graphics, 2 folders
      - 1985 (Box 6)
      - undated (Box 6)
      - Architecture 552/562-Comprehensive Design, 12 folders (Box 6)
      - 1981 (Box 6)
      - 1982 (Box 6)
      - 1983 (Box 6)
      - 1984 (Box 6)
      - 1985 (Box 6)
      - 1986 (Box 6)
      - 1987 (Box 6)
      - 1988 (Box 6)
      - 1989 (Box 6)
      - 1990 (Box 6)
      - 1991 (Box 6)
      - undated (Box 6)
    - University of Michigan, College of Architecture and Design, Assignments and Projects, Pencil and marker on mylar (Map-case 250, Folder 47)
- Drawings 1946-1993
  The records in the Drawings series, 1946-1993 (46 oversize folders) document many of Balogh's architectural projects, including his student work at the University of Michigan and projects in Plymouth Township. The series is divided into two subseries: Architectural Drawings and Miscellaneous Drawings.
  - Architectural Drawings
    The architectural drawings subseries includes Balogh's architectural commissions, as well as materials on the design of his own home and his student work. The files are organized alphabetically by project name, and include information on project location and date, when available. These records include sketches, renderings, design development, architectural, structural, and mechanical drawings. Some files contain materials from all stages of the design process, while others have a smaller number of materials. Media in this series include pen, pencil, and photostatic ink on tracing paper, vellum, paper, and mylar. The series also has blue-line and sepia prints.
    - American Synthetics Company, Scottsdale, AZ, June 24,1983, Pen and pencil on mylar; blue-line prints; renderings; architectural drawings of plans, elevations, sections, details; mechanical and plumbing drawings (Folder 1)
    - Andres, Mr. and Mrs. Fred, Residence, Canton, MI November 2, 1976, Marker and pencil on vellum; renderings; architectural drawings of floor plans, elevations, sections, details (Folder 2)
    - Arizona Historical Society Museum undated, Marker and pencil on mylar; renderings; architectural drawings of floor plans, elevations, sections (Folder 3)
    - Ash, Mr. and Mrs. L. David, Residence, Farmington Township, MI March 17, 1967, Pencil on vellum; architectural drawings of floor plans, elevations, sections, details; structural, electrical, and heating drawings (Folder 4)
    - Balogh, Mr. and Mrs. Tivadar, Residence, Plymouth Township, MI November 7, 1958, Pencil on mylar and vellum; colored pencil on paper; ink on board; blueprints; blue-line print construction drawings; design development drawings; renderings; architectural drawings of plans, elevations, sections, and details (Folder 5)
    - Beck, Mr. and Mrs. Charles B., Organ Studio, Ann Arbor, MI August 2, 1991, Pencil and photocopy on mylar; architectural drawings of floor plans, elevations, sections, details; electrical drawings (Folder 6)
    - Business and Residential Blue-line Prints, Blue-line prints; architectural and construction drawings (Folder 7)
    - Callow, Mr. and Mrs. James, Residence, Livonia, MI June 8, 1990, Blue-line prints; construction drawings (Folder 8)
    - Canton Township Agricultural Shelter, Canton, MI March 24, 1984, Pencil on mylar; renderings; site plan (Folder 8)
    - Chen, Residence May 3, 1993, Pencil on vellum; blue-line prints; architectural drawings of floor plans, elevations, sections, details; electrical and structural drawings (Folder 9)
    - Clark, Mr. and Mrs. Samuel K.
      - Residence, Plymouth, MI November 19, 1962, Blue-line prints; floor plans, elevations, sections, details (Folder 9)
      - Residence, San Cristobal, Mexico January 3, 1973, Blue-line prints; floor plans, elevations (Folder 9)
    - Cohen, Dr. and Mrs. Carl, Residence, Ann Arbor, MI March 25, 1990, Pencil on vellum; floor plan (Folder 9)
    - Constant, Dr, and Mrs. Errikos, Residence, Meridian Township, MI July 30, 1974, Pencil on vellum; colored pencil on paper; blue-line prints; renderings; topographical survey; architectural drawings of floor plans, elevations, sections, details; electrical and structural drawings (Folder 10)
    - Crown Alloys Company, Madison Heights, MI November 10, 1993, Blue-line prints; construction drawings (Folder 11)
    - de Bear, Mr. and Mrs. Richard, Plymouth, MI, Residence, June 23,1978, Pencil on mylar; ink jet on paper; blue-line prints; design development drawings; architectural drawings of floor plans, elevations, sections, details (Folder 12)
    - Fabian, Vclav, Residence, Lansing, MI March 16, 1978, Pencil on vellum and mylar; architectural drawings of plans, elevations, sections, details; electrical drawings (Folder 13)
    - Fairmont Builders (Folder 14)
      - Emerald Lake II/ Heartwood Subdivision, East Lansing, MI May 12, 1988, Pencil on vellum and mylar; colored pencil on paper; blue-line prints; renderings; design development drawings; architectural drawings of floor plans, elevations, sections (Folder 14)